Hello everyone, welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And I'm Erika.
我是Erika。
And today we're going to be going to one of the least favorite places of many, many people.
今天我们要去一个很多人都不太喜欢的地方。
So it must be the dentist.
那一定是牙医诊所了。
Exactly.
没错。
That place where you have to go every six months, but...
那个你每六个月就得去一次的地方，但是……
You probably don't go.
你可能根本不去。
You probably don't.
你很可能不去。
I know I don't go every six months.
我知道我自己就没做到每六个月去一次。
So yeah, we're going to be going to the dentist and of course we're going to be looking at
所以，是的，我们要去牙医那里，当然我们也会学习
a lot of great vocabulary related to teeth and all that crazy stuff dentists do.
很多与牙齿相关的词汇，以及牙医做的那些疯狂事。
Yes.
是的。
And we'll also learn some really interesting phrases.
我们还会学到一些非常有趣的短语。
So Marco, let's get started with our vocabulary preview.
那么Marco，让我们开始今天的词汇预览吧。
Vocabulary preview.
词汇预览。
Okay, in vocabulary preview today we have two words.
好的，在今天的词汇预览中，我们有两个词。
Let's take a look at the first one.
让我们先看第一个。
Toothache.
牙痛。
Okay, so we've seen before this ending ache, right?
好的，我们之前见过这个后缀“ache”，对吧？
Right.
对。
It means it hurts.
它的意思是“疼痛”。
Exactly.
没错。
So again, a toothache would be?
那么，“toothache”就是？
A hurting tooth.
牙齿疼。
Yes.
是的。
We can also say stomachache, headache.
我们也可以说“stomachache”（胃痛）、“headache”（头痛）。
Yep.
对。
Pretty much everything can...
几乎任何东西都可以……
Ache.
痛。
Yeah.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
So our next word, x-ray.
那么下一个词，“x-ray”（X光）。
X-ray.
X光。
X hyphen R-A-Y.
X，连字符，R-A-Y。
Okay, pretty easy word.
好的，这个词很简单。
So when you go to the doctor, many times you'll get an x-ray.
所以当你去看医生时，很多时候你会拍X光片。
It is a picture of your bones.
那是你骨骼的照片。
Right.
对。
So that's an x-ray.
那就是X光片。
All right.
好的。
Well, we're going to hear both of these words in the dialogue.
嗯，我们会在对话中听到这两个词。
So why don't we listen as Gary visits his dentist?
那么，我们不如听听Gary去看牙医时的对话吧？
Hey, Gary, great to see you again.
嘿，Gary，很高兴再次见到你。
Please have a seat.
请坐。
So tell me what seems to be the problem.
告诉我哪里不舒服。
Thanks, doc.
谢谢，医生。
I've got a really bad toothache.
我牙痛得厉害。
I can't eat anything.
我什么都吃不了。
And look, my face is all swollen.
你看，我的脸都肿了。
I think it might be my wisdom teeth.
我想可能是我的智齿出了问题。
Well, let's have a look.
嗯，让我看看。
Open wide.
张大嘴。
This doesn't look good.
情况看起来不太好。
Well, it looks like you have a cavity and your crown is loose.
嗯，看起来你有个蛀牙，而且牙冠松了。
You'll need to put in a filling before it gets any worse.
你需要补牙，以免情况恶化。
And the crown probably needs to be refitted.
牙冠可能需要重新安装。
I'm going to order some x-rays.
我要给你拍几张X光片。
Is it going to hurt?
会疼吗？
No, not at all.
不，一点也不疼。
Just lay back and relax.
躺下放松就好。
Okay, spit.
好了，吐出来。
Okay, that always happens.
好吧，这种事总是发生。
The dentist says, no, it's not going to hurt.
牙医说：“不，不会疼的。”
Don't worry about it.
“别担心。”
But it always hurts much more than he says.
但实际上总是比他说的疼得多。
Exactly.
没错。
So in this dialogue, we saw some interesting words when the dentist was describing what
所以在这个对话中，我们看到了一些有趣的词，是牙医在描述
problems Gary had.
Gary的问题时用的。
Yes.
是的。
So why don't we look at those now in Language Takeaway.
那么，我们不如在“语言要点”环节中看看这些词。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
All right, let's take a look at our first word.
好的，让我们看看第一个词。
So Gary said that his face was all swollen.
Gary说他的脸都肿了。
Swollen.
肿的。
So swollen is an adjective, right Marco?
所以“swollen”是形容词，对吧，Marco？
Right.
对。
So his face is or was swollen.
所以他的脸是肿的。
It was bigger.
它变大了。
Yeah, his face was bigger than normal.
是的，他的脸比正常情况大。
Yes.
是的。
Often when you hurt yourself, that part of your body becomes swollen.
通常当你受伤时，身体的那个部位会肿起来。
Swollen, right.
肿的，对。
So you have to put some ice on it usually and then the swelling will go down.
所以通常你要敷点冰，然后肿胀就会消退。
And that's the noun, the swelling.
那是名词“swelling”（肿胀）。
Right, the swelling.
对，肿胀。
And well, the verb to swell.
嗯，动词是“to swell”（肿胀）。
All right, three words for the price of one.
好的，一个词三种形式。
So let's listen to some examples of how we would use the swelling, swollen and to swell.
那么让我们听一些例子，看看如何使用“swelling”、“swollen”和“to swell”。
Example one.
例子一。
My nose is swollen.
我的鼻子肿了。
It's the size of a football.
它像个足球那么大。
Example two.
例子二。
Put some ice on your foot and the swelling will go down.
在你的脚上敷些冰，肿胀就会消退。
Example three.
例子三。
I got bitten by a spider and my hand is swelling up.
我被蜘蛛咬了，手正在肿起来。
All right, so Gary's face was swollen and he thought that it was his wisdom teeth.
好的，所以Gary的脸肿了，他认为是他的智齿出了问题。
Wisdom teeth.
智齿。
Okay, so this is interesting.
好的，这很有趣。
Wisdom is like wise.
“Wisdom”是“wise”（智慧）的意思。
Yeah, knowledge.
是的，知识。
Knowledge.
知识。
Yeah.
是的。
So these teeth, they're not knowledgeable, but they're called wisdom teeth.
所以这些牙齿，它们并不有知识，但被称为智齿。
They're the teeth that grow last in your mouth, right?
它们是嘴里最后长出来的牙齿，对吧？
Right, they are the last teeth at the very end of your mouth.
对，它们是嘴巴最里面的最后几颗牙。
Yes, and usually you get them when you're about 20.
是的，通常你在20岁左右长出来。
And since they come out at this age, sometimes they interfere or they hurt a little bit,
而且因为它们在这个年龄长出来，有时会干扰或有点疼，
so you have to get them taken out.
所以你可能需要拔掉它们。
Yes.
是的。
All right, wisdom teeth.
好的，智齿。
Wisdom teeth.
智齿。
Okay, now for our next word and something that we all got as children.
好的，现在看下一个词，我们小时候都经历过的东西。
Cavity.
蛀牙。
A cavity.
一个蛀牙。
It's a hole in your tooth.
就是牙齿上的一个洞。
A hole in your tooth.
牙齿上的一个洞。
And it's caused by?
它是由什么引起的？
Too much sugar.
吃太多糖。
Too much sugar, right?
吃太多糖，对吧？
Or not brushing your teeth enough.
或者刷牙不够。
Yeah.
是的。
So that's why everyone had it, I think, as children.
所以我想每个人小时候都得过。
Cavities.
蛀牙。
I never had a cavity.
我从来没有蛀牙。
Really?
真的吗？
Yeah.
是的。
Wow, didn't have much sugar?
哇，没吃太多糖？
I guess I was a bit of a health nut when I was a kid.
我想我小时候算是个健康狂人。
Well, no, I wasn't.
嗯，不，我不是。
My mom was.
是我妈妈是。
No, I guess not.
不，我想不是。
All right, but enough about my eating habits.
好了，关于我的饮食习惯就聊到这里。
Let's talk about our next word, crown.
让我们谈谈下一个词，“crown”（牙冠）。
Crown.
牙冠。
A crown.
一个牙冠。
So a crown, this is interesting.
所以“crown”，这很有趣。
We're not talking kings and queens.
我们不是在说国王和王后。
That's the first thing that comes to mind, right?
那是首先想到的，对吧？
No, a crown is actually the visible part of your teeth.
不，牙冠实际上是你牙齿的可见部分。
Okay, so there's one part of your tooth that's inside that you can't see, right?
好的，所以牙齿有一部分在里面你看不到，对吧？
That's called the root.
那叫牙根。
Yes.
是的。
So when he said your crown is loose, was he talking really about the actual tooth?
所以当他说“你的牙冠松了”时，他真的是在说牙齿本身吗？
So sometimes people will lose a tooth or have a really bad cavity.
所以有时人们会掉牙或蛀牙很严重。
So the dentist needs to make a new crown or a new visible part of the tooth for you.
那么牙医需要为你做一个新的牙冠，也就是牙齿新的可见部分。
So sometimes it'll be made of gold.
有时它会用金子做。
Yep.
对。
Or porcelain.
或者瓷器。
Porcelain, exactly.
瓷器，没错。
So a crown, it's like a really, really, really big filling.
所以牙冠就像一个非常非常大的补牙材料。
A crown.
牙冠。
So his crown needed to be refitted or put back into place.
所以他的牙冠需要重新安装或复位。
Yes.
是的。
Now our final word, filling.
现在最后一个词，“filling”（补牙材料）。
Filling.
补牙材料。
A filling.
一个补牙材料。
So I just said this word previously.
我刚才说过这个词。
Now when you have a cavity, you need to fill it in.
当你有蛀牙时，你需要把它填上。
Right, you need to fill it with something.
对，你需要用东西填满它。
Yes.
是的。
It's usually some sort of paste.
通常是一些糊状物。
And it gets really hard, just like your tooth.
然后它会变得很硬，就像你的牙齿一样。
Exactly.
没错。
So then it covers up this cavity.
这样它就能盖住这个蛀洞。
Filling.
补牙材料。
A filling.
一个补牙材料。
I have many fillings.
我有很多补牙材料。
I wasn't very healthy as a kid.
我小时候不太健康。
All right, not a good toothbrusher.
好吧，不是个好刷牙的人。
Exactly.
没错。
So why don't we listen to this dialogue again, and then we'll come back and talk a little
那么，我们不如再听一遍这个对话，然后回来聊聊
bit about some of the interesting phrases that the doctor used.
医生用的一些有趣的短语。
Hey, Gary.
嘿，Gary。
Great to see you again.
很高兴再次见到你。
Please have a seat.
请坐。
So tell me what seems to be the problem.
告诉我哪里不舒服。
Thanks, Doc.
谢谢，医生。
I've got a really bad toothache.
我牙痛得厉害。
I can't eat anything.
我什么都吃不了。
And look, my face is all swollen.
你看，我的脸都肿了。
I think it might be my wisdom teeth.
我想可能是我的智齿出了问题。
Well, let's have a look.
嗯，让我看看。
Open wide.
张大嘴。
This doesn't look good.
情况看起来不太好。
Well, it looks like you have a cavity, and your crown is loose.
嗯，看起来你有个蛀牙，而且牙冠松了。
We'll need to put in a filling before it gets any worse.
我们需要补牙，以免情况恶化。
And the crown probably needs to be refitted.
牙冠可能需要重新安装。
I'm going to order some x-rays.
我要给你安排拍几张X光片。
Is it going to hurt?
会疼吗？
No, not at all.
不会，一点也不疼。
Just lay back and relax.
躺下来放松就好。
Ah.
啊。
OK, spit.
好了，吐出来。
Well, the dentist used three really interesting phrases, and I want to look at the first
嗯，牙医用了三个非常有趣的短语，我们先来看第一个
one.
短语。
What seems to be the problem?
有什么问题吗？
OK.
好的。
It's a very easy little sentence to ask somebody what's wrong.
这是一个非常简单的小句子，用来询问别人怎么了。
Exactly.
没错。
Right?
对吧？
And I mean, these are small, easy words, but when you put them together, they sound
我的意思是，这些都是简单的小词，但把它们组合在一起，听起来
really natural and really fluent.
非常自然、非常流利。
So if you ask somebody what seems to be the problem, it's very polite, and it's a very
所以如果你问别人“有什么问题吗”，这非常礼貌，而且是一个
good way of asking what's wrong.
很好的询问出了什么状况的方式。
Yes.
是的。
All right.
好的。
Our next phrase, also made up of simple words, let's have a look.
下一个短语，也是由简单的词组成，我们来看一下。
Let's have a look.
我们来看一下。
So this is a phrase that maybe your mechanic or your dentist or your doctor will say.
所以这个短语可能是你的修理工、牙医或医生会说的。
Or anyone.
或者任何人。
Right.
对。
Let's have a look.
我们来看一下。
Let's look at it and see what the problem is.
我们检查一下，看看问题出在哪里。
OK.
好的。
Let's have a look.
我们来看看。
OK.
好的。
And our final phrase, it doesn't look good.
还有我们最后一个短语：情况不妙。
It doesn't look good.
情况不妙。
So I can use this phrase for an object, right?
所以我可以把这个短语用在物体上，对吧？
Yeah.
是的。
Like, this house doesn't look good.
比如，这房子看起来不好。
Yes.
是的。
But here it's used a little bit differently.
但这里用法有点不同。
So why don't we listen to some examples to help us understand the meaning?
那我们听几个例子来帮助理解意思吧？
Example one.
例子一。
John told me it doesn't look good for me.
约翰告诉我，我的情况不太乐观。
I probably won't get the job.
我可能得不到这份工作了。
Example two.
例子二。
It doesn't look good for Michael Jackson.
迈克尔·杰克逊的情况不太妙。
He's in a lot of debt.
他负债累累。
Example three.
例子三。
No, the economy doesn't look very good.
不，经济形势看起来不太好。
OK.
好的。
So in the examples, we can see that they are using it for the situation.
所以在例子中，我们可以看到他们是用它来形容局势。
Yeah.
是的。
It looks maybe problematic.
看起来可能有问题。
Yeah.
是的。
So when you say it doesn't look good, you basically mean there are going to be problems.
所以当你说“情况不妙”时，基本上意味着会有麻烦。
All right.
好的。
It doesn't look good.
情况不妙。
Yeah.
是的。
OK.
好的。
So great phrases, great words.
很棒的短语，很棒的词汇。
Let's listen to our Gary at the dentist one more time.
我们再听一遍加里在牙医那里的对话。
And then we'll come back and talk a little bit more.
然后我们再回来多聊一点。
Hey, Gary.
嘿，加里。
Great to see you again.
很高兴再次见到你。
Please have a seat.
请坐。
So tell me what seems to be the problem.
告诉我哪里不舒服。
Thanks, Doc.
谢谢，医生。
I've got a really bad toothache.
我牙疼得厉害。
I can't eat anything.
我什么都吃不了。
And look, my face is all swollen.
你看，我的脸都肿了。
I think it might be my wisdom teeth.
我觉得可能是智齿的问题。
Well, let's have a look.
嗯，让我看看。
Open wide.
张大嘴。
This doesn't look good.
这看起来不太妙。
Well, it looks like you have a cavity and your crown is loose.
嗯，看起来你有个蛀牙，而且牙冠松了。
We'll need to put in a filling before it gets any worse.
我们得在情况恶化之前补上。
And the crown probably needs to be refitted.
牙冠可能也需要重新调整。
I'm going to order some x-rays.
我要安排拍几张X光片。
Is it going to hurt?
会疼吗？
No, not at all.
不会，一点也不疼。
Just lay back and relax.
躺下来放松就好。
Okay, spit.
好了，吐出来。
Well, Marco, speaking of dentists, have you ever had an experience like this where you
嗯，马可，说到牙医，你有没有过这样的经历，在牙医那里
spat out a tooth at the dentist?
吐出一颗牙？
Well, nothing so serious as this, but actually, recently when I was in Cambodia...
嗯，没这么严重，但最近我在柬埔寨的时候……
Oh, right, you called us in Cambodia.
哦，对了，你在柬埔寨给我们打过电话。
Yeah.
是啊。
Well, our taxi driver offered us to have some local food.
嗯，我们的出租车司机请我们吃当地食物。
And he said, well, we're going to have a dog.
他说，我们要吃狗肉。
So that was interesting.
那还挺有意思的。
Actually, it wasn't that bad.
其实，味道没那么差。
It was pretty good.
还挺好吃的。
But, you know, if you get around the fact that it's a dog...
但是，你知道，如果你忽略那是狗肉的话……
So what does this have to do with your teeth?
那这和你的牙齿有什么关系？
I was eating it and I bit a bone that was hidden.
我吃的时候咬到了一块藏着的骨头。
And I chipped my tooth.
结果我的牙崩了一块。
So you broke part of your tooth.
所以你牙齿碎了一部分。
Yeah, like half of it, which I had already chipped before.
是啊，大概一半，而且之前就崩过。
So I had to go to the dentist.
所以我得去看牙医。
And so the dentist created a new crown, not with gold or porcelain, actually with a paste.
然后牙医给我做了个新牙冠，不是用金或瓷，而是用一种糊状物。
And then it becomes hard and it just looks normal.
它变硬后看起来很正常。
It doesn't even look like I have a fake crown, so to say.
甚至看不出来是假牙冠，可以这么说。
But dentists can be really expensive.
但牙医可能很贵。
So how much did this cost?
那花了多少钱？
Well, this was for the bargain price of $10.
嗯，只花了10美元，很划算。
$10.
10美元。
That's how much it cost.
就花了这么多。
So we should all go to Cambodia for dentistry.
所以我们都该去柬埔寨看牙。
Yeah, because actually it was pretty good.
是啊，因为其实还挺不错的。
He looked really young, though.
不过他看起来真的很年轻。
I was kind of scared because when he walked in, he looked like he was 19.
我有点害怕，因为他走进来的时候看起来像19岁。
But I asked him his age and he was like 30.
但我问了他的年龄，他说30岁。
OK, well, you're very trusting.
好吧，你还真是容易相信人。
Yeah.
是啊。
So I imagine that you guys maybe have some dental experiences.
所以我想你们可能也有一些看牙的经历。
So why don't you come to our website and tell us all about it?
那不如来我们的网站跟我们聊聊吧？
Yeah, visit us at EnglishPod.com and you can find lots more resources for learning English
对，访问EnglishPod.com，你还能找到更多学习英语的资源。
there.
在那里。
Well, guys, thanks for listening and until next time.
好了，各位，感谢收听，下次再见。
Bye.
拜拜。